<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian liberty described in a sermon preached in the Collegiate Church at Westminster, by a minister of Suffolke. A.C.</title>
            <author>Chapman, Alexander, 1576 or 7-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4960.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836726</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69092)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 824:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian liberty described in a sermon preached in the Collegiate Church at Westminster, by a minister of Suffolke. A.C.</title>
                  <author>Chapman, Alexander, 1576 or 7-1629.</author>
                  <author>Barlow, William, d. 1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. VV[indet] for Matthew Lawe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A.C. = Alexander Chapman.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to William Barlow.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 1448 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1012:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTIAN Liberty Deſcribed in a SERMON PREACHED IN the Collegiate Church at Weſtminſter, by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Suffolke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non legem vereor nocens, ſed fortunam innocens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. C.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed. by <hi>I. VV.</hi> for <hi>Matthew Lawe.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1012:2"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
               <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>will proue vnſauerie: for corrupt ſtomacks turne good meate into loathſome parbreakes. Their iudgement is little worth, who like of nothing, but what they doe themſelues. When this Sermon was preached, applauſe enſued: the printing (I truſt) will not diminiſh the preachers prayſe.</p>
            <closer>De abſentibus bona.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1012:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>GAL. 5.13.</bibl>
                  <p>For Brethren yee haue beene called vnto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, onely vſe not your Libertye as an occaſion to the fleſh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not miſery ſo much as ſtrangenes, if as ſome of our antie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Religious</hi> iudged, it be mans beſt to liue a kinde of priſoner; or, if, as deuout S. <hi>Bernard</hi> wiſhed, to be alwaies ſickly; or, if obedience (which includeth ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection and reſtraint) be, as <hi>Plato</hi> writeth, mans not onely choiſe, but alone virtue; as if his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe were ſuch, that hee coulde not liue but by rules and directions, or his frowardnes of will ſo vnruly, that he cannot haue any liberty, but hee will abuſe it. It muſt be true, that without law there cannot bee offence, and yet it is better and
<pb facs="tcp:1012:3"/> leſſe offence, to ſuffer the lawes tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then to be without the lawe; <hi>Praeſtat illic eſse vbi nihil li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, quam vbi omnia.</hi> It is better to be there where nothing is lawfull, then where all thinges; where there is no liberty then nothing but liberty; where a man may do euill, then where hee can neither do good nor euill. Reaſon of this can there none be giuen, but a miſdoubting fear, that man left free to the liberty of a bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dles and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite will, woulde act ſomewhat more at length, then man can define or ſay what; the practiſe of an endleſſe, mad, and inconſiderate will, beeing far beyond the conceit of mans limited inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Man is impatient &amp; cannot beare reſtraint (a note, not of his natures; generouſnes &amp; worth but vntamed wildnes, and inſolent hautineſſe) &amp; yet he is not at all to be borne, if not reſtrayned (a note againe not of his infinitenes and power, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntrary, of his imperfection &amp; corruption) from the firſt, not able to do that is good; from this ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, willing to do nothing but that is euill. Is not the frowardneſſe of man ſtrange, that hee ſhould, <hi>In vetitum ruere &amp; negata cupere</hi> more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire an euill thing beeing forbidden, and not the more alſo affect a good thing, for being inhibited (which nothing els in the world doth, but man, reſtraint of it ſelfe, hauing equall effect in both; &amp; yet the ſtate ſo, that the euill vpon neceſſity muſt
<pb facs="tcp:1012:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> bee forbidden to man, or elſe it will bee worſe.) Vpon theſe difficulties, is it not very odde? that a like courſe of the Romane law-giuers muſt be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, who, to auoid <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> held it their onely meanes, to command that nothing ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the Church. And that of <hi>Lycurgus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Decem Tab. opes amoue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> who to take away <hi>ielouſy,</hi> held it his only way, to make <hi>adulterie</hi> to be no ſinne; courſes I cannot reſolue whether in theſe particulars, good for a common wealth or no, but in a Chriſtian Church intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and yet wiſedome naturall cannot tell, how to giue a better remedy. The good &amp; wiſe God of <hi>nature,</hi> foreknowing the vnrulines of <hi>Liberty</hi> hath ſo contriued the whole frame and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of man, that there is not a power in him, that hath not (as it were) a propper limiter and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to it. The natural vnſatiate appetite of the bodyes noriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, it is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with the ſtreight compaſſes of the bodyes inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, with ſenſe of paine from oppreſſion, with delight from ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency; the mindes paſſions and affections, ſome of them bounded by ſhame, ſome by feare, all by reaſon; Reaſon it ſelfe, by innated concluſions; the will and deſire, by vnderſtanding; the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, by the will and deſire, <hi>vt voluntas oculis, ſic intellectus fertur carere pedibus;</hi> the will wanteth eyes, &amp; ſeeth nothing, but by the vnderſtanding; ſo the vnderſtanding wanteth feete, and can fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb facs="tcp:1012:4"/> nothing, but by the will; will &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding limited by memories &amp; imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s imperfect preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by outward ſenſes imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillities &amp; ſcarcity of obiect; ſenſes &amp; all the ſoule power &amp; ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> led by the bodies terrene groſnes; the body it ſelfe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fined by a ſhort &amp; ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der skin &amp; <hi>ſuperficies;</hi> &amp; that alſo by a proper place inferiour here below, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the baſeſt eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And thus as man; God bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded man. And yet behold thus inchained (as it were) and impriſoned in him ſelf, man, hee will bee free, nay hee will bee wild, and this his ſcanted liberty will breake out looſe, into an infinity of vncontrouls and freedoms of diſorders. His naturall appetite, for that it hath <hi>libertye</hi> to deſire, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l neuer but deſire &amp; will not be ſatiſfied with ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, his aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will deny obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto Reaſon, and plead it their King: but at pleaſure &amp; by election, oftner is reaſon depoſed by rebellious affections, then affections held obedient ſubiects by Reaſon; His deſire, ſwels infinit &amp; wil haue more then is, more then inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can form, &amp; fancie &amp; vnderſtanding, ſhewe his vnderſtanding will dreame and prate, and tell of more then it can conceiue and approue, from ſimilitudes of ſenſe; ſenſe, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth almoſt natures playnes, and wil haue <hi>Arts</hi> more curious obiects and repineth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be tyed to the bodyes organs. The baſe body diſdaines to dwell belowe, &amp; will build a Tower, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it may
<pb facs="tcp:1012:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> climbe vnto the heauen. Thus man, confined from vice (his whole compoſe and make being nothing (as it were) but a miſtery of linkes, and chaines of inhibition, one vnto another) &amp; ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, almoſt, of all free libertye, yet ſee how, the ſmall he hath, he doth abuſe, as if he were alone to be compeld and gouerned. The God of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, well diſcerning this manner of mans cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſuted agreeably a courſe vnto him, and gaue him at length new lawes <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. auſtere and ſtrict, binding him to perfourmance vnder ſeuere penalties, reſtraints that would giue but a ſhorted liberty, and burthens that hee could not with eaſe diſport him vnder. And thus God delt with man. Is it not ſtrange, it ſhould be cenſured and found the better, for man to liue vnder <hi>Lawe</hi> then <hi>Libertye?</hi> that man (the worthieſt &amp; nobleſt of Gods creatures, by creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both good &amp; wiſe) ſhould rather doe that he ſhould, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a command, then <hi>liberty,</hi> and direction of his owne abilities? that the writing of <hi>lawes</hi> in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſhould more auaile with him, then ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them in his heart? Or is not the temper of man ſtrangely miſwrought, by corruption, that it ſhould be eaſier for God (as I may ſo ſpeake) to write his lawes in ſtones, in hard tables of ſtone, then firmely enough to engraue them in his heart? <hi>Reuerence</hi> of <hi>vertue</hi> is humanities religion; <hi>ciuility</hi> is the goodnes; and credit all the <hi>holynes</hi> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:1012:5"/> 
               <hi>pietye:</hi> and then ſhall man ſo farre degenerate, as rather to practiſe that, which is made but good, by the force of a commande, then reuerence vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue his owne proper obiect, &amp; from it ſelfe good and excellent? Shame is the property of man, from which a true ingenuous ſpirit will more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde diſgrace then danger, and feare it more to take diſcredit, then a wound; and then, ſhall feare (that common quality with beaſts) reſtraine man more from vice, &amp; hold him better in obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? ſhall he endure better to ſerue, then to obey, and to obey then to command? whoſe priuiledge &amp; prerogatiues were <hi>Liberty</hi> &amp; <hi>rule,</hi> and to bee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto neither of the two? yea thus diſordered is corruption, which being, not a thing that was created and made, is not a ſubiect to be diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, thus, with <hi>Natures</hi> &amp; <hi>Reaſons</hi> grounds and principles. Man thus indured long, a ſeruant to lawes, commands both inferior and ſtrict, they were <hi>burthens</hi> inſupportable; names, the one of <hi>ſlauery,</hi> the other <hi>miſery:</hi> the <hi>law</hi> it yoked man, a reſtraint both hard and baſe; it was a ſchoolmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that taught with whips and rods, &amp; nothing but ſeuerity, mans chief incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was feare &amp; tenor; his vttermoſt diligence not toil inough; his deſert, puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; his reward future &amp; but hopes of promiſe; his reuerenteſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>prieſthoode,</hi> but <hi>birthes gift</hi> (which is deſerts <hi>preiudice</hi>) his worthieſt dutye, but in ſacrificing
<pb facs="tcp:1012:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> beaſtes; for al his noblenes and honor, his chiefe performance was in types and figures; and for all his abilities and worth, his practiſe &amp; action was but in inferior ceremonies. The God of loue &amp; mercy (the fulnes of his time now come, &amp; the praefixed period of his decree expired) came downe from heauen, &amp; left both the right hand and boſome of his father (places, the one of glory the other of loue) and vouchſafed to deſcend <hi>(a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris &amp; humilitatis progreſſus eſt deſcenſus)</hi> nay to the inferiority &amp; condition of a cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ture (a thing eſpecially againſt the nature of a God and a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) &amp; beeing here amongſt vs, did not conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and triumpher-like, abrogate &amp; diſanull our former lawes, to impoſe more ſtrict &amp; harder of his owne, from glory and policies ſeuerity; but firſt (and that for our ſake) he fulfilled them, that his obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce might be righteouſnes to many;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> he freed vs from the curſe of the law, by being made himſelfe a curſe for vs,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>Non authoritate Regis ſed obedientia filii,</hi> not by the abſolute authority of a King, but by the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a ſon; not by ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the bond, but by paying the debt, not alone by giuing mercy, but by ſatiſfying iuſtice; not by being graced by fauour; but by ſuffering pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: He took thoſe heuy burthens from our ſholders, &amp; eaſed vs of them (at leaſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> much light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he took vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the law, &amp; placed vs vnder grace, &amp; cal'd vs, as my text doth ſpeak to <hi>liberty.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1012:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> And this is, as I take it, the trueſt inference of my text. The methode I will obſerue in handling, ſhalbe this. Firſt, after a ſhort <hi>Apology</hi> and reaſon for my <hi>Texts</hi> choice, I will premiſe ſomewhat of <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> in generall: Secondly, I will giue the ſeueralles and particulars, wherein this <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath called vs vnto, conſiſteth, Thirdly, preſent vpon euery particular of our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> I will adde the peculiar and proper fleſhly abuſes of them. This <hi>text,</hi> it is ſo difficult, that <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen,</hi> euen <hi>Origen</hi> himſelfe <hi>(quem Chriſtiani Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetam, Philoſophi magiſtrum dixerunt)</hi> ſaith <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lirinenſis,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">In comment. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> locum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (a)</note> did iudge it to be obſcure; And <hi>S. Hierom,</hi> ſo abſtruſe, that he thought it his beſt to follow <hi>Origen,</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>Origen</hi> had for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merly iudged it to be obſcure, as if his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of it were this, that he gaue the beſt iudgement, whoſe iudgement was not abſolute. If this obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity deterreth not the naturall forwardneſſe and boldnes of youth, from medling with it (as why ſhould endeuours of difficulty be rather exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from it; then aduentures of dangers) yet may it vnhappely breede the cenſure of arrogancy, or of an <hi>indecorum</hi> and <hi>indiſcretion,</hi> which all, but <hi>ſchollers,</hi> do more auoide then arrogancy. Nay rather why ſhould not the hardnes of it, excuſe me if I do it not well, then terrefy me from atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it, for feare of doing it ill; and <hi>Origens</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of obſcurity, bee my iuſt <hi>Apologie? Caluin</hi> is
<pb facs="tcp:1012:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> cenſured to haue been learned in <hi>Diuinity</hi> by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching others, not by being firſt taught himſelfe: or, fullier to excuſe my ſelfe; as <hi>S. Hierom</hi> (in his 1. proeme vpon this epiſtle) to <hi>Paula</hi> and <hi>Euſtochiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> writeth, <hi>S. Paul</hi> did in this epiſtle to the <hi>Gallat.</hi> So will I; I do not purpoſe ſo much to teach as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, <hi>Non tam docere, quam reprehendere &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepare:</hi> And though it ſeemeth not ſo to you, <hi>Minus quiddam eſt increpare, quam docere,</hi> to teach re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quires maturity of iudgement; to finde fault with abuſes, onely a good intention is ſufficient to do it truly, and a little common vnderſtanding to do it perfectly. And why ſhould not <hi>Elder Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort young <hi>Timothy</hi> to rebuke with freedome, except it be now feared, that then young <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> would rebuke old <hi>Paul.</hi> But if from this my freedome, which I purpoſe, in reprouing our <hi>Church</hi> abuſes you ſhall miſconceiue my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by iudging it inclinable to ſome other <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Romiſh,</hi> and <hi>Papiſticall ſuperſtition,</hi> you ſhall not more againſt <hi>Charity</hi> then <hi>reaſon</hi> it ſelfe offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and iniure me. I haue read an antient father deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Adultery,</hi> to bee nothing els, but a <hi>Curioſity of an other mans pleaſure;</hi> in which ſenſe, I <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promiſe for my Conſciences Chaſtity, that ſhee plaieth not the adultereſſe in Curioſity of another plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor the faith</hi> and <hi>Opinion of any other Church, then this of ours which I am truly wedded vnto.</hi> Nay ſhould a man be touched, either by loues feare, or enmities <hi>ſuſpition,</hi> with ſuch an odiouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:1012:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> as the <hi>Papacy</hi> amongſt vs; I would not wiſh him make that vulgar forme of <hi>Apologie,</hi> by running preſently into an immoderate commendation of <hi>his Churches goodneſſe (Speciem illud haberet &amp; ſimilitudinem adulationis,</hi> that would haue the ſhew and reſemblance of <hi>flattery</hi>) nor would I wiſh him to conceale her <hi>faults; ſilence</hi> of <hi>faults,</hi> is a kinde of baſer flatterie, not wiſer; and for mine owne part, I had rather bee naught my ſelfe, then flatter them that bee ſo. Nor would I wiſh him runne into an eager deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſpraiſe of the impoſed ſcandall, for that would preſently be cenſured, either <hi>falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> and <hi>disſimulation,</hi> or <hi>malignitie,</hi> from the braine or ſpleane, not from the hart: but I ſhould rather aduiſe him, freely of himſelfe to ſpeake the vttermoſt, that wiſer <hi>Auditors</hi> might diſcouer the <hi>fallacies,</hi> that gaue occaſions of the vniuſt <hi>ſuſpicion.</hi> And this premiſed, I come neerer to the matter. For the doctrine of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Libertie</hi> in generall, <hi>Caluin</hi> (whom eſpecially I purpoſe to follow.) In the 19. <hi>Chapter</hi> of his 3. booke of <hi>Inſtit.</hi> vrgeth the explication of this <hi>Chriſtian Libertie,</hi> as a thing not to be omitted, by him, who will compriſe in ſhort, the ſumme of the whole <hi>Goſpell;</hi> as if he meant it an <hi>Epitome</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianitie:</hi> and placeth it not onely amongſt things commendable, but commendeth it in the degree of <hi>neceſſity;</hi> that without it the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> can attempt nothing, without
<pb facs="tcp:1012:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>doubting wauering, varying, trembling, deſpairing,</hi> nor euer attaine the doctrine of <hi>Iuſtification:</hi> as if <hi>Chriſtian Libertie</hi> were the <hi>rule,</hi> for <hi>conſciences,</hi> to ſquare their actions by. This I deny not; the doctrine of this <hi>Libertie</hi> is good and neceſſarie, but take heede <hi>you abuſe it not as an occaſion to the fleſh. Chriſtian Libertie,</hi> it is more neceſſary to be <hi>knowne,</hi> then <hi>commended</hi> or <hi>vrged:</hi> who deſires it not, if he doe but know it; who vſeth it not, if he doe not know it? I am afraid, men ſhould make it their <hi>aſylum,</hi> refuge, and comfort, in their looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diſorders. This doubt is not mine; <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin</hi> himſelfe foreſaw this eaſines of abuſe &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſently vpon his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation preuenteth thus. <hi>Simulat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iniecta eſt aliqua mentio Chriſtianae libertatis, ibi aut ſer ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t libidines, aut inſani motus ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, niſi maturè obuiam eatur laſciuis ingeniis iſtis: partim e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m huius libertatis praetextu omne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excutiunt, &amp; in effraenata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> licentiam ſe prori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt, partim indignantur putantes omne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moderatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rerumque delectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tolli.</hi> If the particulars be well marked, had <hi>Calu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> beene the <hi>author</hi> of our <hi>diſorders,</hi> he could not better haue deſcribed our <hi>times Caluin,</hi> in his wiſdome forelawe theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, before they came; <hi>Sic Sapientia, diuinatio eſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pomponius Atticus) So wiſedome is a diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> though contrarie, with other <hi>Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Diuinatio ſapientia ſuit, Diuination</hi> hath beene their <hi>wiſedome,</hi> by foretelling of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents which they entended to effect, though
<pb facs="tcp:1012:8"/> by diuining, in the nature of giuing warning, they ſo purchaſed the opinion of integrity and good meaning. The doctrine of Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it was more neceſſary when <hi>Paul</hi> did preach; when none of the Gentiles or Iewes receiued Chriſt; when a Church was to bee eſtabliſhed, then now in a full ſetled <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> where no man doubts of it. <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> be properly oppoſite in ſome reſpects; and therefore where <hi>Atheiſme</hi> is more feared then <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme</hi> there <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> muſt be warely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. This made <hi>antiquity</hi> rather clog the <hi>Church</hi> with ſuperſtition, and too much then too little, as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> aduiſeth in his <hi>Ethyckes,</hi> to bend moſtly to one ſide, when nature is more propenſe vnto the other. To vrge <hi>liberty</hi> vnto the multitude &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuppoſe an exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil reſtrain exceſſe, is, as if one ſhould put a ſtrong bit and bridle, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a fierce courſers head, but then turne him out looſe into the champaine, and ſuppoſe he will bee guided well inough. The miſunderſtanding, nay miſteaching, this <hi>Liberty</hi> amongſt ſome forraine <hi>Diſciplinarians</hi> haue taken thoſe effects, that one may almoſt ſay of them as <hi>Plutarch</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his <hi>Lacon. Apothe.</hi>) reporteth one to haue ſaid of <hi>Athens:</hi> One (ſaith hee) travayling to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> and ſeeing the <hi>Athenians</hi> to reuel &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton it, in all laſciuious and licentious delights <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in honeſtum ducere,</hi> and nothing to account diſhoneſt, returning home againe and aſked how
<pb facs="tcp:1012:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> matters went at <hi>Athens,</hi> he anſwered that <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia pulchra,</hi> all there was well, all there good, <hi>per iocum innuens, omnia illic pulchra putari, turpe ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil;</hi> Ironically inſinuating, that all things there were accounted good and nothing diſhoneſt. In ſomwhat ſuch like ſort returning trauailers from thoſe <hi>licentious Reformers,</hi> may almoſt report as truly that <hi>Omnia illic pulchra,</hi> all thinges there be faire, all things there chriſtian: that which once was vice is now with them no vice, that which once was vertu, is now none, as if vices &amp; virtues had held their eſſences but by leaſe; which now expired, they ceaſe to be that which they were before <hi>vices</hi> &amp; <hi>virtues.</hi> So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what like to that which was wrot of <hi>Petronius Arbiter</hi> (pardon the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance whatſoeuer <hi>Petronius</hi> was) may be ſaid of theſe men. <hi>Illi dies per ſomnum, nox oblectamentis vitae tranſigebatur, vtque alios induſtria, ita hunc ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauia ad famam protulerat;</hi> he ſpent the day in ſleepe, and the night in the pleaſures of the life; &amp; as <hi>Induſtry</hi> made famous other men, ſo did <hi>ſloth</hi> him: <hi>habebaturque non ganeo &amp; profligator, ſed eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dito luxu.</hi> So theſe, in the day and ſight of men, as a ſleepe, they doe no more but breath; but in the night and ſecret, then they play their <hi>prankes</hi> And as ſtrictneſſe and auſterity of life, made famous and renowmed our aunceſtors; ſo looſeneſſe and liberty theſe; and yet they muſt not be ſaid to be <hi>Libertines,</hi> but of a learned
<pb facs="tcp:1012:9"/> &amp; <hi>Zealous Luxury (freedom</hi> I ſhuold haue ſaid) &amp; <hi>chriſtian liberty.</hi> Thus ſlippery &amp; eaſy, yea, almoſt neceſſary is the lapſe vnto theſe abuſes; when <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> is immoderately, inconſiderately and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly taught and commended. Men in their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of pleaſure, will not diſtinguiſh <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>licence,</hi> in which, deuotion alſo hauing a part, which neuer thinkes it goeth far enough, will neuer iudge they haue vſed <hi>liberty</hi> aright, till they be at the furtheſt of <hi>licentiouſneſſe.</hi> Strange it is how farre men will runne poſſeſt with beliefe that vpon <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Gods law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> they ought to take a <hi>liberty.</hi> I will beſtowe but one note more vpon this point: Allegation of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, is a note of faction in the common wealth; and pleading for <hi>liberty</hi> is alwaies to bee ſuſpected &amp; many times it is a mark of <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> in the Church. It is an odd obſeruance which <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>melius</hi> maketh vpon that of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his preſcriptions of <hi>Apelles</hi> the heretick, ſeduced by <hi>Philumena. That there was neuer yet Hereticke who pleaded not for his liberty. Qui ſuas non habuerit Philumenas,</hi> that hath not had his <hi>Philumena</hi> ſpeaking in that particular <hi>Liberty</hi> for al. I therfore, in ſhort will conclude this part with the aduiſe of <hi>Galba</hi> to <hi>Piſo</hi> adopting him Emperor (for that which he ſpake of the Romans is true of vs) That in teaching this doctrine wee<note place="margin">Tacit. lib. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:1012:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ought to be very wary, and to conſider, that wee are to deale with men, <hi>qui nec totam ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitutem pati poſſunt, nec totam libertatem,</hi> who can neither beare onely ſeruitude, nor onely <hi>Liberty.</hi> I come now to the <hi>particulars</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Chriſtian Liberty conſiſteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caluin</hi> (my guide in the fore-named place) thinketh it to conſiſt in three things;<note place="margin">Inſtit. 19. c.</note> 
               <hi>Primae vt fidelium conſcientiae dum fiducia ſuae Coram Deo inſtificationis &amp;c.</hi> firſt that the Conſciences of the faithfull, whileſt they ſeeke a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their iuſtification before God, may lift <hi>themſelues</hi> aboue the <hi>Law totamque legis inſtitiam obliuiſcantur,</hi> and forget all the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the law for ſince the law leaueth no man iuſt, either wee are excluded from all hope of iuſtification, <hi>aut ab illa nos ſolui oportet</hi> or we muſt be freede from it; <hi>Ac ſic quidem, vt nulla prorſus operum ratio habeatur,</hi> and ſo freed that no regarde that all bee had of workes <hi>Nam qui vel tantillum operum ſe afferre debere ad obtinendam iuſtitiam cogitat,</hi> for hee that thinketh hee ought to bring neuer ſo little of workes to obtaine iuſtice, hee maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the debtor of the whole law; <hi>ſublata igitur legis mentione &amp; omni operum cogitatione ſepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita</hi> the very me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioning therfore of the law being taken away, and al cogitation of works, he muſt in
<pb facs="tcp:1012:10"/> the matter of <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> onely imbrace the mercy of Chriſt. So <hi>Luther</hi> to this purpoſe is very much, in his bookes <hi>de libertate Chriſtiana,</hi> and his <hi>Comment.</hi> vpon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Gal.</hi> where,<note place="margin">Vt Bellar. de Iuſtif. li. 4. cap. 1.</note> vpon the 2. Chapter thus, <hi>Sola fides ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria eſt, vt iuſti ſimus, caetera omnia liberrima, neque praecepta amplius neque prohibita.</hi> Againe, <hi>Si conſcientia dicat, peccaſti; Reſponde, peccaui: ergo Deus puniet &amp; damnabit; Non: at lex hoc dicit; ſed nihil mihi cum lege: quare? quia habeo libertatem.</hi> Let all this be true, but take heede <hi>you abuſe it not as an occaſion to the fleſh.</hi> The great <hi>Cardinall</hi> controuerſor of our daies, <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> vpon this or ſuch like ſpeeches paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thus his cenſure; <hi>Iſta, quomodocunque ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſentur, certè magnam vim habent, ad perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum ſimplici populo, &amp; ad malum propenſo, non eſſe facienda opera bona:</hi> Theſe how ſoeuer they may bee excuſed, verely they haue great force to perſwade the people, being ſimple, and propenſe to euill, that good <hi>workes</hi> are not to be done. May I ſay, without a kinde of ſinne againſt this place, that there is moderation in this cenſure? yes, for an aduerſaries. Nay then thinke of it well, and tell me; doe you your ſelues iudge it eaſie, for ignorance and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the one to conceiue, the other to beleeue, ſuch hard doctrines and ſeeming repugnances as theſe be? namely, that we are freed from the
<pb facs="tcp:1012:10"/> morall Law, and yet to our power to performe it; that we haue nothing to doe with the Law (but with faith in <hi>Chriſt</hi>) and yet the <hi>Decalogue</hi> not to be neglected; that <hi>good workes,</hi> are not ſo much as to be thought on for <hi>ſaluation,</hi> and yet to be performed? will not corruption (thinke you) be vnwilling, and ignorance vnable to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh theſe, &amp; ſo betwixt them both let good workes alone? whatſoeuer the ſenſe be of them, what may be; nay the ſound alone wil be enough for vnwillingneſſe to omit them, and guiltineſſe to apologie for them hauing omitted them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie. I would to God I were not here conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to runne into complaintes (that vnfitting ſubiect for a yoong mans toonge) no man lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing better then my ſelfe to ſpeak that may <hi>pleaſe,</hi> though no man hating it more then to ſpeake to pleaſe. All Stories haue complained of their times, I know it well, and know not any, that haue not cryed out <hi>ô tempora, ô mores;</hi> but yet ſome haue complained more then others, and euery one (if well obſerued) of ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vice or other: but none in generall haue complained more then this our age (the ſenſe and ſight of the preſent doth not deceiue me) and none ſo much of vncharitableneſſe, ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe had not where to lay his head; it is our p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r and times proper vice. Will yee in this particular, ſee the true diſtinction
<pb facs="tcp:1012:11"/> betwixt our aunceſtors and vs; <hi>Illi vitiis labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabant, nos remediis;</hi> they laboured with vices, we with remedies; they were ſicke with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, we with Phiſicke: the firſt is alwaies pittied, this ſecond (in ſmaller matters) is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally laughed at. Or if you will, thus. The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world is ſicke of a diſordered Ague; the whole fitte from vnnaturall and diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red heate; that now is paſt, and of it we haue no feare, hauing had ſo ſtrong purgations. And now the colde ſhiuering fitte of indeuotion and vncharitableneſſe is ſore vpon it. Had all things in the world decaide ſo much as chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world, before this time, had beene as ſmall as a moate. Doe I ſlaunder and ſcandalize our time? Why tell me then, come not good lawes from euill manners? were not our forefathers conſtrained by <hi>Statutes,</hi> in one kinde, to moderate deuotions <hi>charitie:</hi> and are not <hi>our Parliaments</hi> inforced to ſtrengthen <hi>Lawes,</hi> and enact new, for reliefe of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? and yet will not our newe <hi>Lawes,</hi> ſupply the place of olde <hi>deuotions charitie.</hi> Wiſedome in <hi>Salomons</hi> time, cryed in the high ſtreetes, and amongſt the preſſe at the entring of the gates, and none would heare her; now wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (God be thanked) is heard reſonablie well, but <hi>pouertie</hi> lyeth crying, not amongſt the preſſe at the entrings of the gates, but in
<pb facs="tcp:1012:11"/> the <hi>porches</hi> of the <hi>Temples</hi> of the Lord, cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſo neere his houſe and altars as they can, the more to moue compaſſion, but euery one paſſeth by, and ſcarcely looke vpon the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man; Nay, the <hi>Leuite</hi> (the <hi>Prieſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) commeth through the porch, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vp into his pulpit, and there ſpeaketh ſo for <hi>Chriſtian Libertie,</hi> that hee little commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Chriſtian Charitie,</hi> or any whit helpeth the poore wounded man. Of this vncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, may it be vn-offenſiue to ſeeke the cauſe? was it a religious hate of an olde abuſe, and a <hi>flight</hi> from that opinion of meriting by works, to the extreame oppoſite? No, that courſe is iudged to be erroneous, and by the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our better writers, to haue miſlead,<note place="margin">Hooker.</note> and done ſome harme, in many particulars of <hi>Reformation.</hi> And the very <hi>Poet</hi> telleth vs,<note place="margin">Horat.</note> that <hi>In vitium ducit culpae fuga, ſi earet arte,</hi> the flying of a <hi>vice</hi> leadeth to a vice, if it wanteth Art; and let vs be aſhamed to alleadge it, we ſhall be accuſed of folly, <hi>Si in contraria cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus;</hi> Nay let vs feare to alleadge it, <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> maketh it a preſcription againſt worſe then follie, to runne rather from an opinion then to one; <hi>Opus hoc eſt habere non de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio aedificio ſed alterius deſtructione, ſuffode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne non aedificare:</hi> As if our Religion ſhould bee, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> writeth, of the nature of <hi>Galba,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1012:12"/> to be rather <hi>extra vitia quam intra virtutes.</hi> What then is the cauſe? I dare not preſume to giue the cauſe of any thing, and leſſe of euills, then bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, but if I may coniecture it to bee that which others of vnderſtanding, haue plainely iudged it to be; I then ſuppoſe it verely, that our abuſes in neglect of charity, haue come from thoſe former named poſitions, not that they be erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but erroneouſly vnderſtood and abuſed. And ſo in this ſenſe, I will ſay with an aduerſary himſelfe, who layeth it an imputation vpon vs, that vncharitableneſſe and euill life, be not onely from our corrupt natures, but alſo from our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; not that theſe doctrines, be properly cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them, but rather occaſions taken from theſe and ſuch like poſitions, our aduerſaries do take aduantage to abuſe vs, by perſwading their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, that we do teach licentiouſneſſe: So <hi>Bellar.</hi> himſelfe doth from thoſe (as he ſaith) of the rigid <hi>Lutherians In Colloquio Altenburgenſi, ad ſatanam ſpectare Chriſtianos cum operibus bonis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Adeo non eſse neceſſaria opera bona, vt etiam ad ſalutem incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſuntque pernicioſa. Precari oportere vt in fide ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne omnibus operibus bonis, vſque in finem perſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</hi> with diuers like, which I confeſſe in their ſenſe may be true, but yet had neede to meete with better interpreters, then aduerſaries or igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rants. And your vnderſtandings know; that if an aduerſary can take aduantage, to abuſe vs from
<pb facs="tcp:1012:12"/> them, we our ſelues will take occaſion, to abuſe them to our owne aduantage of liberty: loue of liberty in our ſelues, will work as ſtrongly, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice can in others. VVhat ſhould I recount par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. From this part of <hi>chriſtian liberty,</hi> I will not ſay, but inconſiderate vrging of it, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiuing, haue come a multitude, if not <hi>ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Paradoxes,</hi> yet of <hi>ſchiſmaticall practiſes and manners; Equidem viri fratres, Mores noſtri ſunt ſciſmatici,</hi> verely <hi>brethren,</hi> many of our manners, they be <hi>ſchiſmaticall:</hi> there is no greater <hi>hereſie</hi> of life, then is <hi>vncharitableneſſe.</hi> Hence, firſt, there is a ſecret couert for <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> which in the <hi>inuiſibilitie</hi> of <hi>ſole faith</hi> (from hence miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) may freely <hi>couſen</hi> and <hi>diſſemble;</hi> hence <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid ſecurity,</hi> which vnder the opinion of <hi>certaintye</hi> and <hi>ſufficiency</hi> of beliefe alone, layeth ſound and dead a ſleepe, (a ſleepe on both eares) <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>conſcience. Laborioſa quondam res fuit eſſe chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, nunc ingenioſa,</hi> It was once a matter of labor to bee a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> now of <hi>diſpute</hi> &amp; <hi>talking;</hi> once of <hi>practiſe,</hi> now of <hi>doctrin</hi> only. Hence next what if I ſhold obſerue to haue come, that very <hi>Paradox</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſtes. That al things muſt be common: For, Church reuenewes</hi> taken away <hi>houſes</hi> of <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> ſuppreſt, and <hi>charity</hi> (vpon this doctrine) buried in their ruines, <hi>neceſſitye</hi> inuented this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox,</hi> to haue it ſelfe maintained, a <hi>ſubtill policy</hi> of the <hi>Diuell,</hi> vnder a falſe ſhew of greater <hi>Charitye</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1012:13"/> to take away all charity, by induc ng a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Hence alſo commeth iniurious ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and traducing, the <hi>religious liues</hi> and courſes of once renowmed <hi>ſaints;</hi> to the preiudice of <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture charity,</hi> and iniury of former. And hence <hi>vngracefull reprochings</hi> of <hi>Charities liberality,</hi> and olde deuotions goodly monumentes: which, as their abuſes gaue ſome cauſe, ſo the inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate teaching this doctrine, gaue occaſion to <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full authority</hi> for to <hi>ſuppreſſe.</hi> I cannot name them but I muſt ſpeake a word or two. <hi>Faire</hi> porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Lord</hi> they were, which to beſtowe vpon him, <hi>deuotion</hi> diſinherited her owne deare children, <hi>faire Paradiſes</hi> (the fathers call them ſo) where innocency might beſt haue kept it ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, but <hi>ſubtill ſerpenty,</hi> intiſing to a taſte of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruite, both ſhee and hers were ſtreight <hi>diſparadiſed;</hi> ſince when, in ſweate and ſorrow, haue wee their ſucceſſors eat our bread, and the earth it bringes forth many <hi>thornes</hi> and <hi>thiſtles</hi> for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> portions. I thinke the <hi>ſuppreſſion</hi> of thoſe <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents</hi> (of that nature) that it was a puniſhment but iuſt and firſt deſerued. Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty is not limited to a good cauſe, but in caſe of miſery is common to al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: you may bewaile the death of him that dieth iuſtly, &amp; therfore neede not feare to <hi>lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> their <hi>ouerthrow.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood it was for <hi>Ceſar</hi> that <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> ſhould not liue; yet when the head of worthy <hi>Pompey</hi> was ſhewed vnto <hi>Ceſar,</hi> the ſtory ſaith, he
<pb facs="tcp:1012:13"/> wept moſt bitterly: ſo, if we any where behold, the remaining <hi>reliques</hi> of thoſe goodly walles digd vp with the <hi>bones</hi> of them that fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them; though ſo well done, mee thinke wee ſhould not chuſe but weepe moſt bitterly. I will ſay but a word more of them, The pulling of thoſe buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings downe, was of the nature of thoſe thinges <hi>quae defendipoſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſed &amp; defleri.</hi> O vſe not then thus your <hi>liberty</hi> as an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the <hi>fleſh</hi> No, no, this <hi>chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liberty,</hi> it is not an immunity from mercies <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſions</hi> and <hi>charities good works,</hi> but it is a ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude vnto them, as the words next vnto my <hi>Text</hi> do ſpeak, exhorting, that by loue we ſerue one an other. <hi>Religion</hi> is not a <hi>breſt-work,</hi> there is no ſuch <hi>freedom</hi> from the <hi>law;</hi> it is not inough for <hi>charity</hi> to hold her hand on her boſome and feele how her hart worketh, but from her hart ſhe muſt ſtretch it forth to help the diſtreſſed. A <hi>chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as he hath a Creed to belieue ſo hath he x comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to obſerue: Chriſt</hi> came not to <hi>diſſolue</hi> the <hi>law,</hi> but to <hi>fulfil it.</hi> In the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> there bee not onely <hi>Conſolations,</hi> but <hi>threats</hi> and <hi>Comminations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 7.</note> 
               <hi>The t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that bringeth not foorth good fruits ſhalbe cut downe and throwne into the fire.</hi> The <hi>Goſpell</hi> preached as it ſhould, will make <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> cry out, <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> what ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e do?<note place="margin">Act. 2. Iames. 5.</note> and not onely, I will go in peace, my faith hath ſaued me. <hi>Iames</hi> preached <hi>Goſpell,</hi> when hee bad
<pb facs="tcp:1012:14"/> the rich men hold. The <hi>Euangelium,</hi> it is a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and good meſſage; who doth deny it; for that it telleth of our <hi>ſauiour</hi> and <hi>reconciler;</hi> but it hath other <hi>offices;</hi> The promiſes of it, be <hi>free, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall,</hi> and <hi>mercifull;</hi> but many of them be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall, <hi>Fac hoc &amp; viues. Mat.</hi> 19. <hi>Si vis ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ingredi, ſerua mandata:</hi> And obedience to the <hi>Lawe morall,</hi> is as well taught in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> as in the <hi>Lawe: Chriſt</hi> he was a <hi>Law-giuer,</hi> as well as a <hi>Redeemer</hi> from the <hi>Lawe.</hi> The yoke of <hi>Chriſt</hi> it is ſweet but yet a yoke; and his burthen is light, but yet a burthen. Why, but how then (wil you ſay) are wee freed from the <hi>Lawe?</hi> As I euen now tould you out of <hi>Caluin,</hi> for I do not contradict him, but you, that abuſe his doctrine; yet if you will, in a word I will tell you whatſome others write, wee are freed, ſaith the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> from the burthens of the <hi>iudiciall</hi> and <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> law; of which ſpake <hi>Peter</hi> Act. 15. <hi>Quid tentatis imponere iugum ſuper Ceruices Diſcipuloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quod nec nos nec pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres noſtri portare potuimus;</hi> what but onely ſo? are we not freed from the <hi>morall law?</hi> yes, thus ſome write we are, <hi>a Dominio legis moralis;</hi> It ruleth not ouer vs as ſlaues, but childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is made more ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable and light vnto vs, for that the law came alone, but the Goſpell with grace. They which receiued the <hi>Lawe</hi> in <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued only doctrine, that, inſtructed by the lawe, they might diſcerne betwixt <hi>vices</hi> and <hi>virtues:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1012:14"/> but they which receiued the <hi>Goſpell</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued alſo <hi>grace</hi> with it; not onely to diſtinguiſh good and euill, but to loue goodneſſe and hate iniquitie. Before, it was the Lawe of <hi>ſeruitude</hi> and <hi>feare,</hi> for that without <hi>grace,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> could not giue; it placed men guiltie and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the puniſhment; but now by Chriſt it is the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Libertie</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> for that he giueth with it his Spirite, making vs more able and willing to performe it, and addeth, by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, to our want and imperfection in it. It is Saint <hi>Auguſtines Simily in Lib. de perfect. iuſtitiae.</hi> That the <hi>Lawe</hi> now, it is like vnto the winges of a birde, which doe not ſo much <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe</hi> as lighten vp; the winges of themſelues be <hi>heauie,</hi> but hauing giuen them a power to moue, they be no burthens to the body, but an eaſe and lightening. In a word, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath <hi>freede</hi> vs from the <hi>Lawe, non adimendo tegi vim obligandi, ſed addendo hominibus charitatem illam libenter implendi.</hi> Or thus, if you will, with Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> That we are, <hi>in lege, non ſub lege.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In 1. Pſal.</note> In the <hi>Law,</hi> not vnder the <hi>Law.</hi> He is ſaid to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>law, Qui a lege agitur tanquam ſeruus,</hi> who is driuen and compelled by the <hi>law</hi> as a ſeruant; he is in the <hi>law, Qui ſecundum legem agit vt liber,</hi> who worketh according to the <hi>lawe</hi> as a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. In a word, <hi>vbi Spiritus Domini, ibi liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. And thus much for this firſt part
<pb facs="tcp:1012:15"/> of <hi>Chriſtian Libertie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pars liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</note> The ſecond followeth, which dependeth (as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſpeaketh) of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and it is this: <hi>Vt conſcientiae, non quaſi legis neceſſitate coactae, legi obſequantur; ſed legis ipſius iugo liberae, voluntati Dei vltrò obediant:</hi> That our conſciences ſhould obey the Lawe, not as compelled by the neceſſitie of the Law, but free from the yoake of the <hi>Law,</hi> ſhould of their own accord obey the will of God; Thus <hi>Caluin</hi> in his former cited place. His meaning, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, from that which followeth, it is this; mans greateſt <hi>perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction</hi> is <hi>imperfection,</hi> his <hi>holineſſe</hi> is <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> his will <hi>vnwillingneſſe,</hi> his <hi>endeuours vaine,</hi> his <hi>paines vnprofitable,</hi> &amp; all his well-done <hi>workes</hi> but <hi>well-dooing euill,</hi> if examined by the rigor and ſtrictneſſe of the <hi>Law:</hi> and therefore now we are freed from that exactneſſe which the <hi>lawe</hi> requireth, our actions are not to be iudged by the letter and tenor of that; but we may like children, offer vp our imperfect, <hi>Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diata opera, aliquid etiam vitij habentia.</hi> Our halfe <hi>workes</hi> (ſaith he) yea hauing ſome fault or vice in them, truſting that our <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>indeuour</hi> wil be accepted by our mercifull Father. And that ſuch we ought now to be, who muſt aſſuredly beleeue, <hi>Obſequia patri probatum iri quantulacun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſint, &amp; quantumuis rudia &amp; imperfecta;</hi> that our performances will be allowed of our Father, whatſoeuer they be, and how rude and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb facs="tcp:1012:15"/> ſoeuer. Let this be true, but take <hi>heede</hi> you <hi>abuſe</hi> not <hi>this libertie as an occaſion to the fleſh.</hi> If as <hi>Symonides</hi> in <hi>Plutarch, Rudiores dixit eſſe Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, quàm qui ab ipſo decipi poſſunt;</hi> So the vulgar they be too ſimple to miſconceiue from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>doctrine,</hi> and make collection, that good <hi>workes</hi> (vpon <hi>this Chriſtian libertie</hi>) are not at all to bee practiſed (for it is an vnhappineſſe of witte to bee caught with <hi>Paradoxes</hi>) yet heere is a <hi>doctrine</hi> more fitte to be abuſed by all conceites and conditions. As this poſition is true and religious, ſo is it wiſe and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, giuing and referring our actions and all of them to the glorie alone, the will, mercie, loue, ſauour and acceptance of God, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether aſſuming libertie vnto our ſelues <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>incluſiuely</hi> (if not warily vnderſtoode) extending <hi>Gods</hi> will, fauour, mercy and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptaunce to the qualitie of our actions. Though to doe nothing ſeemeth not to any ſufficient, yet to doe ones indeuour and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, ſeemeth to all to bee very reaſonable, though ones indeuour be alſo of it ſelfe nothing. The doctrine of this latter (of doing ones inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour) is better than the other (of doing nothing) &amp; yet the effect of them both in practiſe all one, namely <hi>nothing. Hypocriſie</hi> may freely deceiue others; &amp; negligence, it ſelfe; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſufficiency of mens actions, is referred to the cenſure of the
<pb facs="tcp:1012:16"/> ſecret wil of God, and not the ſentence of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward written lawe. And therefore, as religion muſt teach the firſt words of my <hi>Text,</hi> of our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to libertye; ſo muſt wiſedome the latter that <hi>we abuſe it not as an occaſion to the fleſh;</hi> you muſt not conceiue (which is the vſuall abuſe this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine worketh) that you haue <hi>Liberty,</hi> freely to ſquare your actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, not to a law but to the merciful accepta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Gods wil; &amp; then Gods wil by your own inſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cies indeuors; and then your inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors ſufficiency by your own reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; your iudgement by your deſires; &amp; your deſires by your fanſies, and your fancies by your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and your pleaſures by your ſelfe. No, this is the ſame which the Apoſtle here dehorteth from, &amp; yet it is the circle <hi>(vtitur Demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> circulis non rectis lineis)</hi> wherewith the <hi>Diuell</hi> deceiueth the weake eye of ignorance and corruption. But for that this ſecond part of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth (as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſpeaketh) of the former, of which I haue ſpoken more liberally, I thus leaue it, with this light touch I haue giuen it, and come to the third and laſt part of this <hi>Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tertia pars.</note>The third part of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> (ſaith mine author <hi>Caluin</hi> lib. 3 <hi>inſtit:</hi> Cap: 19.7.) is this: <hi>Vt nulla rerum externaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (quae per ſe ſunt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione coram Deo teneamur, quin eas nunc</hi> § <hi>vſurpare nunc omittere indifferenter liceat,</hi> That wee are not bound with any <hi>Religion</hi> before God, to the <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance
<pb facs="tcp:1012:16"/> of outwarde things,</hi> which in themſelues are indifferent, but that we may vſe them or omitte them, indifferently, at our pleaſures. And here be compriſed (ſaith he) all <hi>free ceremonies,</hi> to the obſeruance of which, our conſciences bee tyed with no neceſſity. Let this be true to <hi>faction</hi> or <hi>deuotion,</hi> but take heede you abuſe it not as an <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> to the <hi>fleſh; Gladius hic ille eſt,</hi> this is the ſword firſt kild our enemies, but now hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our owne ſelues, with many feſtring cuts &amp; gaſhes, vpon the hart dangerouſly, vpon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy pittifully, vpon the face moſt deformedly. This got reformation the victory, and made it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it when it had it. <hi>Hannibals</hi> triumphs in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and brauing of the walles of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of <hi>Carthage;</hi> God graunt it bee not ſo with our Church victories in this particular. Can an argument be good againſt the validity of the lawes of <hi>Rome,</hi> as lawes, and not bee as good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lawes of <hi>England</hi> in this kinde. I will ſpeake of this doctrine as <hi>Tacitus</hi> doth of the dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linges of <hi>Tyberius, Quanto maiore libertatis imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne teguntur, tanto cruptura ad infenſius ſeruitium,</hi> with how much the more flattering colour of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> they be couered, ſo much the more euil they appeare at length, to lead to a more troubleſome and ſlauiſh ſeruitude. It is but a firſt thought for any man to imagine, <hi>Peace</hi> a neceſſary cauſe of controuerſies and diuiſions, eſpecially in matter
<pb facs="tcp:1012:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> of diſcipline, where authority is <hi>monarchicall</hi> and abſolute, that may then the better ſuppres them. And cannot any man name <hi>countries</hi> in <hi>chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome quiet</hi> and at <hi>reſt,</hi> that are not thus troubled with diſſentions, nor accuſed of ſuch <hi>liberty</hi> in diſorders? No, the cauſe of our <hi>differences, ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Church factions,</hi> and halfe our vngodlines, hath come from the abuſe of <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> in generall, and from this part of it eſpecially in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular which indeede is no true part of it. As in the two former parts I onely ſhewed the abuſes of them, ſo in this, it was my purpoſe (vpon the firſt choice of this <hi>Text</hi>) to haue ſhewed it, it ſelfe to be an abuſe, and no true part of <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> but the neceſſity of the former parts carrying me thus farre, I will onely adde a word or two of the abuſes of the doctrine. <hi>Lentae aduerſum imperia au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res,</hi> euery mans care is ſoft for impreſſion, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and ſtretched out a length, againſt governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It was the concluſion of the <hi>Rebell Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his oration vnto his <hi>faction;</hi> that they ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther follow him <hi>Gloriae &amp; libertatis ducem,</hi> a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of glory and <hi>Libertye,</hi> then <hi>Segeſtes, flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſae ſeruitutis ducem,</hi> a Captaine of wicked ſeruitude. But why and when wicked ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude? <hi>Non cum impiis Dominis ſeruiatur, Sed quod ſeruire impium;</hi> not when wicked maiſters bee ſerued and obeyed, but that it is a wicked thing to ſerue, ſay our <hi>Arminii.</hi> This
<pb facs="tcp:1012:17"/> doctrine was a ſpeedy meanes to free vs from that inſupportable burthen of <hi>lawes</hi> the Church had laide vpon vs; but was it the beſt? hath it more gotte vs a freedome from them, then a freedome and licence to act what wee liſt? In which it is ignoraunce to looke for moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, man not beeing contented (vpon this <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi>) to haue it graunted him, that hee may doe whatſoeuer hee is able, but what he liſt and is willing vnto. The neceſſity and yoke of obedience (vpon conſcience) once caſt off, what creature like to man, in vntamednes and diſorder? There is not that <hi>looſeneſſe,</hi> that <hi>ryotte</hi> that <hi>luxurye,</hi> that <hi>profuſeneſſe of life</hi> that <hi>fancie,</hi> that <hi>conceite</hi> that <hi>inuention,</hi> that <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> of opinion and behauiour and manners, that he will not runne into and maintayne. Doe I ſlaunder corruption? Do I ſcandalize the peruerſneſſe of our nature, and peruert this doctrine? will wee not, or haue wee not gone ſo farre? Nay I will then turne this cenſure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently: It is <hi>Caluins</hi> owne iudgement and experiment (not my reproche) in the 19. of the 3. of his Inſtit: After hee had giuen vs this point of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> he preſently in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſpeaketh againſt two kinde of abuſes of it. Some there bee ſaith he, who interpret it a licence for their ſenſualities, appetites, and libidinous affections, freely without check, to
<pb facs="tcp:1012:18"/> vſe at pleaſure, the gifts and aboundances of Gods bounty: Others who thinke this <hi>licence</hi> not vſed as it ſhould be, except the diſorders be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, in the ſight and conſpect of men. And in the firſt kinde, ſaith <hi>Caluin, Maiorem in modum hoc ſaeculo peccatur.</hi> There is an exceeding offending in this our age. In thoſe dayes when this doctrin was but new, <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaw the ſpeedy effects of it, and that there were abuſes of it moſt exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, til it came to be marked for the ages blemiſh. There is ſcarce a man (ſaith <hi>Caluin</hi>) who is but able to effect it, whom a luxurious ſpender in the garniſh of his table; the glutting of his belly; the decking of his body; the building of his houſes; doth not delight; and who doth not in all kind of delicacies indeuour to exceede all others. But what of this, will you ſay to mee? what maketh this againſt this <hi>Chriſtian liberty?</hi> Why, marke the ſequell of his words, &amp; you ſhal know: where after <hi>Caluin</hi> had recounted, the infinite nouelties of his times diſorders, he addeth this concluſion to his <hi>liberties</hi> a commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>&amp; haec omnia</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſub Chriſtianae libertatis praetextu defenduntur,</hi> and al theſe things be not practiſed, but defended vnder the pretext of <hi>Chriſtian liberty;</hi> alledging that they bee <hi>res indifferentes,</hi> thinges indifferent and ſo to be vſed. O God! ſhall wee leaſe <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>religion</hi> in one thing both together? what meaneth this patronizing of the cauſe with <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1012:18"/> and condemning the effects? or ſhall we ſay that things indifferent, commanded or inhibited by authority, may be omitted or practiſed freely, ſhall we auer it falſly, &amp; then find fault when men do ſo vſe them, vnreaſonably? I am not able to conceiue the miſtery of this teaching, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am compelled to ſay with <hi>Tertullian, Nuſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facilius proficitur quam in caſtris rebellium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 41. Preſ.</note> 
               <hi>vbi ipſum eſſe illic, promereri eſt;</hi> So will I ſpeake of this teaching; there is no better ſucceſfull arguing then in this rebellious doctrine, in which to ſpeak alone, is to proue, &amp; to proue to ouercome; nor can it be excuſed out of the forenamed father that <hi>de papauere fici gratiſſime &amp; ſuauiſſime ventoſa &amp; vana capriſcus exurgit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 56.</note> that it is but as a naughty ground, maketh a good ſeede a cauſe of bad fruit no, the practiſe of the ſecond kind of men, which <hi>Caluin</hi> mentioned, as abuſers of this doctrine, wil conuince it cleerely, that this <hi>falſly</hi> giuen <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an liberty,</hi> is the naturall &amp; genuine cauſe of theſe offences, and that the diſorders be not abuſes, but effects of this <hi>liberty. Errant in hoc plerique,</hi> many erre in this, ſaith he, that as if their <hi>liberty</hi> coulde not be ſafe and ſound except they haue witnes of the practiſe of it do vſe it <hi>fooliſhly</hi> and <hi>promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> Nay (ſaith he) <hi>videas hodie quoſdam, quibus ſua libertas non videtur conſiſtere niſi per eſum carnium die veneris, iu eius poſſeſſionem peruenerint.</hi> you may ſee ſome at this day, who thinke their <hi>liberty</hi> not
<pb facs="tcp:1012:19"/> to conſiſt, nor to be, but by the eating of <hi>fleſh</hi> on <hi>Frydayes;</hi> they thinke their liberty hath no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence or eſſence but in theſe diſorders, nor can they come into poſſeſſion of it, but by commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, and ſo it inforceth them to do them and therefore muſt needes be the true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſer of them. To this ſee what <hi>Caluin</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth, <hi>quod edu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t non reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do &amp;c.</hi> that they eat fleſh on <hi>Frydaies,</hi> I reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it not <hi>quod edu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t non reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do.</hi> O God, is it not inough for man to offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in conceit, but he muſt be impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? muſt ſinne haue a witnes of it, or is it not ſin? &amp; is it not inough for men to offend, but they muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for it; at leaſt, told that they ſhal not be reprehended? O <hi>Liberty,</hi> thou art the cauſe of all, and we are all the worſe for thee. This opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion ſeemeth to be ſtrictly religious in maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not a denyal, but a ſcorne of obedience vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to any but to God immediat; when as (in deed) it is intollerable pride and arrogancy for that they do it not, ſo much, to giue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God onely as for that they cannot bee ſo humble, as to giue any reſpect and reuerence to man. Shoulde the particulars of <hi>ſchiſmes</hi> bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, (conſequents, all vpon this doctrine) I knowe not whether you would more wonder at them, or deteſt them. Firſt, from hence all obedience to <hi>magiſtracy,</hi> it is at one blowe taken away and that very <hi>Paradox</hi> of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes
<pb facs="tcp:1012:19"/> (as <hi>Eckius</hi> ſetteth it downe) plainely eſtabliſhed, <hi>Nulli poteſtati obediend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m:</hi> For, if the magiſtrate, commanding things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, bee not vpon conſcience, to bee obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then can hee commaund nothing, nor is hee to bee obeyed in any thing; all things beeing either commaunded by God, and ſo the obedience to him; or inhibited by God, &amp; ſo not to be commanded by man; or left <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> by God, to bee inioyed or prohibited by man. Next from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth confuſion &amp; diſſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which God is neuer author of, by the <hi>freedom</hi> of this choice in euery thing: and yet I know, theſe men will much commend their vnity, but I muſt ſay with <hi>Tertul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praeſ. 43.</note> 
               <hi>Confuſio reuera ſiue ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta apud huiuſmodi fere non ſunt, quia cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſint non appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſchiſmata, eſt enim vnitas ipſa,</hi> confuſion and ſchiſmes be neuer with ſuch, for when they bee they make no rentes and ſchiſmes, for it is their very vnity it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Lib. 1</note> Their very forme and order is to haue no order nor forme. As <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in his <hi>Annals</hi> of a Tumult &amp; conſpiracy of the legions, ſo will I of theſe, <hi>Nil paucorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctu, pariter ardeſcunt pariter ſilent,</hi> there is not a diſſention of one or two, they altogether ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otte it, but though altogether, yet they ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otte it, they altogether are vnruled but though altogether, yet vnruled, with ſuch an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall concorde in diſcorde, <hi>tanta aequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb facs="tcp:1012:20"/> &amp; conſtantia vt regi crederes,</hi> with ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality &amp; conſtancy, that you would thinke they were gouerned &amp; had a diſcipline. And this you ſee <hi>Tacitus</hi> maketh a note of <hi>faction</hi> in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, and <hi>Tertullian</hi> of <hi>ſchiſme</hi> or <hi>hereſie</hi> in the <hi>Church. Barbaris quo quis audacior,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus, tanto magis fidus, &amp; rebus commotis potier.</hi> So will I ſay of theſe men, <hi>quo quis ſeditioſior tanto fidelior &amp; rebus commotis potior;</hi> the more ſeditious and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comformable, the more faithfull and ſounde and in diſagreement, of the more eſteeme and recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. I know their anſwere to be vſuall; that their confuſed diſſention (if any of them can bee brought to acknowledge any) is but in outwarde rites and toies <hi>Et differentia rituum, commendat do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae vnitatem;</hi> Alas, a ſimple commendation. Nay, but rather, though the cenſure be ſubiect to cenſure, let me aduenture to ſay with <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preſ. 43.</note> That <hi>Doctrinae index diſciplina,</hi> the looſenes of their diſcipline, is a bewrayer of what ſort their doctrine is, <hi>Et quòd de genere conuerſationis, qualitas fidei aeſtimari poteſt,</hi> and that from the kind of their conuerſation, the quality of their faith may bee iudged. Hence further, from this impeachment and minution of authority, and eſtabliſhment of euery particular mans <hi>liberty</hi> of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with an eaſy and ſlippery pace that <hi>Paradox</hi> which <hi>Eckius</hi> (but falſely, as I hope) accuſeth <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of Lib: <hi>de ſeculari poteſtate; quod inter chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos,
<pb facs="tcp:1012:20"/> nulla debet aut poteſt eſſe ſuperioritas ſed vnuſquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que alteri aequaliter ſubiectus eſt,</hi> an opinion againſt the lawes of God, man, reaſon, ſenſe, and nature. Hence next, a particle of this generall, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment and practiſe, firſt, <hi>in the ſtate eccliſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall,</hi> by holding no ſuperiority; no praelacy, no Hierarchy but equality in the miniſtry. A ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer kinde of pride, not that, which contemneth inferiours (from a conceit of ſelfe-excellency) but that, which endureth not and maligneth a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour (from feare of puniſhment and priuety of ſelfe inſufficiency) a <hi>Paradox</hi> perchance well pleaſing to the laity; vnaduiſedly not marking, that beginning in the <hi>Clergy</hi> it would at length,<note place="margin">Many other obſeruations of further abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were here cut off by the time.</note> come creeping amongſt themſelues.</p>
            <p>I will now onely beſtow one further obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation vpon our owne <hi>home-vrgers</hi> of this <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty</hi> and ſo conclude. When <hi>Iulius Agrico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> in his ſecond expedition, had ouercome a great part of this <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> very cunningly with a pleaſing <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Licenciouſneſſe</hi> of life, intiſed the ruder inhabitants, to a liking and imitation of their cuſtoms; the Brittaines preſently taken, fell in loue with all their practiſes, their actions, their habits, and their ſports; <hi>paulatimque diſceſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad delineamenta vitioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and at length they fell alſo to the imitating of their vices, their bathinges their banquettings, and all their luxuries, <hi>Idque tandem</hi> (ſaith the ſtory) <hi>apud imperitos, humanitas
<pb facs="tcp:1012:21"/> vocabatur, cum pars ſeruitutis eſſet</hi> &amp; that at length with the vnſkilfull vulgar, was called humanity, which as a part of their ſeruitude, and a badge of their ouerthrowe, &amp; he was accounted the moſt ciuill and ingenuous man, who imitated the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> beſt, when as indeede hee was the moſt ſlaue, by imitating his <hi>politique ſubduing aduerſary.</hi> In ſome not vnlike ſort, wee now entiſed by the faire ſhew of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian freedome,</hi> do fal in great loue and liking with it, <hi>paulatim<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſcedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ad delineamenta vitiorum,</hi> &amp; at length we come alſo to the imitating and practiſing of the <hi>faire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes</hi> &amp; <hi>vices</hi> of it; and that is called with vs <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> as that other was with them <hi>Humanity, cum pars ſeruitutis ſit,</hi> when as it is a part of ſeruitude, and we ſlaues in it (if duely con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered) to the inuention of ſome one or two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, and to the practiſe of ſome <hi>beginning Church;</hi> and he would be accounted with vs the beſt <hi>reformed Chriſtian</hi> who doth imitate it beſt, when as hee is indeede the moſt ſlaue, by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his <hi>politique ſubduing aduerſary.</hi> To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe wel obſerued a late writer, that the worthines of one (hee nameth <hi>Caluin</hi>) had wrought too much vpon other mens weakeneſſe. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude I will ſay but that onely of theſe <hi>preciſe ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. lib. 1.</note> which <hi>Tacitus</hi> doth of <hi>Aſtrologia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Genus hominum potentibus infidum, ſperantibus fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lax,</hi> they be a kind of people, <hi>treacherous</hi> &amp; <hi>diſloyall</hi> to great
<pb facs="tcp:1012:21"/> men deceitful &amp; falſe to them that hope in them; and I pray God, I may not iuſtly adde that which followeth, <hi>Genus etiam hominum quod apud nos ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabitur ſemper &amp; retinebitur;</hi> they bee a kinde of men, which alwaies ſhall be forbidden, and yet alwaies retayned. No, let them goe, in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moual <hi>pernitioſior quies quam temeritas,</hi> reſt is more pernitious then raſhneſſe.</p>
            <p>The God of might and mercy, giue vs all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>ſpirit</hi> of his <hi>holy Catholique Church,</hi> that is of <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> not <hi>licentiouſneſſe;</hi> of <hi>freedome</hi> not <hi>looſenes,</hi> of <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> not <hi>faction;</hi> of <hi>vnity,</hi> not <hi>diuiſion;</hi> of <hi>wiſedom</hi> &amp; <hi>iudgement,</hi> not <hi>fancie</hi> &amp; <hi>ſingularity;</hi> that all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined in the one and ſingle diuine inſpiration of it, we may vnderſtand our <hi>liberty</hi> rightly; practiſe it vnabuſiuely; in <hi>religious liberality</hi> to the poore <hi>charitably;</hi> in perfourmance of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes (to our power) laboriouſly; in obedience to the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> and his lawes, moſt dutifully; In reuerence to the <hi>Church-canons, Rites</hi> and <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> moſt conſcionably; and thus in loue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all one another moſt <hi>chriſtianly.</hi> This graunt, God the father, the ſonne and the holy ghoſt; to whom be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed al power, might, maieſty, and dominion now and for euer</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
